have you ever considered purchasing a
baseball team my name is Matt and I'm a
current strategy and operations
Associated at Google prior to that was a
Management Consultant at BCG and today I
am going to walk you through how I would
solve a banan company case interview
question but with that let's get right
into it all right so the question reads
as follows our client Alpha capital is a
private Equity Firm that is considering
buying the Philadelphia Phillies the
current team owners approached Alpha
about purchasing the team for $1.1
billion Alpha engaged our firm in the
due diligence process and wants us to
help them understand a what is the team
worth and B should they make this
investment okay so the first thing you
want to do whenever you're given this
kind of a question is you want to take
quick notes now there's two questions at
play here the first is what is this team
worth and the second is should Alpha
Capital invest now these are similar
questions but they're not exactly the
same and so it's important to understand
the distinction between asking what the
value of this team is versus whether or
not they should invest because valuation
is only one aspect that goes into the
decision-making process of whether or
not you should invest in a particular
company or in this case a sports team
and the answer to this question is going
to inform this question but it won't
necessarily be the only thing that we
consider when we answer this question
and so the first thing you always want
to do in a case interview is after
you've taken notes on the prompt you
want to think through a couple
clarifying questions that you can ask or
interviewer now the reason why you want
to ask clarifying questions is because
one it solidifies your own understanding
of the situation and makes sure that
you're not missing out on any important
details and two it gives you an
opportunity to demonstrate that you're
thoughtful and thinking ahead and so I'm
just going to brainstorm a few key
questions here that hypothetically you
could ask these are not the only
questions you could ask there's
technically an unlimited number but you
want to come up with usually at least
two or three okay so I've taken a few
minutes to put together a few clarifying
questions and I'll just walk you through
each of these now so the first question
is what is Alpha capital's investment
strategy now I know this might seem a
little bit basic to be asking but it's
actually a really important question for
us to understand because we know that
Alpha capital is a private Equity Firm
but we don't know what their specific
investment strategy or mandate is and
when I say investment strategy I'm
saying what types of companies or teams
do they invest in do they traditionally
invest in sports teams what is their
typical investment Horizon do they like
to typically buy a business operate it
and improve it for 5 years and then sell
it or are they more of a long-term
investor and they like to hold their
Investments for five plus years also
what is the typical way in which they
fund their investments just because the
purchase price is expected to be 1.1
billion doesn't mean that that entire
1.1 billion is going to be funded by
Alpha Capital they might be raising debt
or outside funds from other investors my
second clarifying question is does the
1.1 billion purchase price include the
team and the stadium or is it just the
team and this is really important
because when we say they want to buy the
Philadelphia Phillies what does this
actually mean to us does this mean it's
just the players or are we talking about
the entire Stadium the seating the merch
and everything else related to the
sports team I would assume that this 1.1
billion means everything related to the
team but it's good to clarify third what
are the major revenue streams again
really important question here how do
they make money what is the business
model I would assume that for a sports
team a major driver of the revenue is
going to be through ticket sales but a
lot of sports teams have additional
revenue streams as well including media
and streaming royalties as well as merch
sales to fans and other ways of
generating additional income from games
and tied to that what are the major cost
drivers of operating a sports team again
very important because in the context of
a private Equity transaction
profitability is going to be critically
important because in private Equity
typically what happens is you put a lot
of debt onto the business or in this
case the sports team and you need the
company to generate enough cash to pay
down the debt over time now these are
just four questions that I've just come
up with off the top of my head
hypothetically you could come up with a
lot of other clarifying questions but
essentially your interviewer will
probably give you some information
related to each of
these and so the next step from here is
you're going to want to go into
developing your framework and the way
you want to do this is you want to just
say okay awesome can I just take a few
minutes now to put together a framework
and you want to take probably 90 seconds
to 2 minutes no longer than two minutes
on coming up with a framework now before
I come up with the framework for those
of you who are not familiar a framework
is simply a fancy word for a set of key
buckets that you want to investigate
related to this problem that we're
trying to solve and it's designed so
that you should be able to tick through
each bucket and eventually get to a
level of confidence where you can make a
solid recommendation as to whether or
not it's a good idea and so I'll give
you an example here okay so I've just
spent a few minutes putting together
this framework now the way that I've
structured this framework is I've split
it into two key buckets and I'll walk
you through how I would explain this to
an interviewer so the first thing you
want to say is awesome so I've taken a
few minutes to put together a quick
framework and now I'd like to walk you
through it so there's two buckets to
this framework the first is financial
considerations related to whether or not
we should invest and the second is
non-financial considerations and so
under Financial considerations broadly
speaking there are four things that I'm
most interested in the first is
valuation purchase price I've kind of
lumped these into the same bucket here
really want to understand how much we
believe this team is actually worth and
likely we'll need to put together our
own analysis to understand the intrinsic
value of this team and compare that of
course to the purchase price which we
know is 1.1 billion but that doesn't
really mean a whole lot to us without
knowing the valuation first and the
second thing is cash flow/ profitability
as we know since Alpha capital is
probably looking to make a positive
return on their investment it would be
good to understand how profitable the
team has been historically as well as
going forward what we think is
reasonable from a cash flow generation
perspective because again in a private
Equity transaction you're typically
going to be putting debt onto the
business and using the cash flows of the
company to pay down that debt over time
and so it's really important for us to
find a company or in this case a team
with stable cash flows if that is the
route that we are taking thirdly really
want to understand sources of funding
and again as I've said there's likely
going to be some debt that gets put onto
this transaction but it would be good to
understand like the proportion of debt
to equity now debt is going to be money
that they're raising from outside
investors and equity is going to be the
portion that Alpha capital is actually
putting in as well into the transaction
and it's good to understand the
proportion of debt to equity because it
gives us a sense of risk related to the
transaction so if for example it's going
to be a 7030 split where 70% is debt and
30% is equity then I might want to have
a conversation with Alpha capitals MD
about hey why do we need to put so much
debt onto this business is it because we
simply lack the funds to actually meet
the entire 1.1 billion purchase price or
is there some other reason in most
scenarios it's it's good to have not too
much debt on the business because if
things do go south they can go south
very quickly I'm not going to spend too
much time talking about that but this is
why funding is really important because
also where are you going to get it from
right like who where and how expensive
is it going to be how much is it going
to cost us to raise that funding
fourthly want to understand any
potential synergies now typically
synergies are more common when you have
a strategic acquirer buying a business
AKA one company buying another company
as a opposed to a private Equity Firm
buying a company as part of their
portfolio but it's still important to
consider because there could be some
possible cost savings related to this
deal or at least ways in which the
private Equity Firm can come in and
either drive up revenue or lower costs
but moving to the non-financial bucket
here I'm interested in again four key
levers the first being competition I
want to understand how the Philadelphia
Phillies Stacks up against the
competition in the league and if we have
other competitors that are more
successful than us then what are they
doing and what sort of best practices
are they doing that potentially we need
to watch out for the second sub bucket
is customer now customer you can really
split into a few different groups but
the biggest one most people are thinking
of is probably the fans that come to
your Stadium but also you could argue
that another customer could be like the
media companies that are buying the
streaming rights to your games right
they're going to pay you some amount in
order to be able to stream your baseball
game live and so with the fans we have
to be really care careful too because
how are the fans going to react when
they find out that a private Equity
buyer is coming in and taking ownership
of this team some of them might get
pissed and also what do they care about
maybe there are certain preferences that
these fans have that we have to be
cognizant of when we're making any sort
of changes to the business after we buy
it and moving down to this third bucket
which is the Players again a lot of the
times the value of the team is going to
be heavily dependent on the players and
if we have a really stacked roster or
not on top of that the player salaries
are probably one of the biggest expenses
that this team has and so we have to
think about things like player attrition
whether or not these players are going
to leave when they find out that we are
going to be the new owners and also how
much are we paying these players what
are the expectations around potentially
signing new player contracts things like
that there's a whole host of
considerations that we have to think
about because the team is so heavily
dependent on the performance of the
players and finally with this fourth
bucket here it's kind of a catch all but
I've just written other growth levers
question mark so is there anything else
on the non-financial side that we can
think of what is part of our plan and
what opportunities are there to
potentially increase the value of the
team and ultimately the value of our
investment and so maybe this is
something like increasing the number of
merch lines that we have maybe this is
pursuing sponsorships with influencers
to drive more traffic to the games maybe
this is implementing some kind of
dynamic pricing situation to drive up
the amount of Revenue that we're
generating a bunch of things could fall
into this bucket but any and all growth
levers we want to brainstorm and think
about so that we can have a good
understanding of what the potential
upside is here and what the private
Equity Firm can actually do to this team
once they purchase it if they do
purchase
it now once you do come up with your
framework what you want to do is you
want to walk the interviewer through at
a high level basically the same way that
I just did here and they may potentially
have some questions for you but if this
is a interviewer-led case then they will
typically point you towards the right
direction or a specific bucket that they
want you to move towards and if it's an
interviewee Le case which most Bane
cases are then the onus is kind of on
you to suggest a bucket that you would
like to dive into first and so in this
scenario let's say for example I'm very
curious about the valuation of the
sports team right because question
number one is what is this team even
worth in the first place and I think a
lot of these other buckets are important
but the number one thing we need to find
out first is how does the valuation
compare to the purchase price and so I
would say something along the lines of
well I think the value Val ation is
really important to understanding
whether or not we should even make this
investment to begin with so I'd like to
start there do we have any information
related to the value of the business or
any information related to revenue or
costs and in this scenario the
interviewer might press you to think a
little bit harder about what the
potential sources of revenue might be
and the reason why I'm asking about
revenue and costs is because at the end
of the day to get to valuation we have
to understand the cash flow of the
business and value the company based on
the present value of its future cash
flows for those who haven't taken a
corporate finance class valuation at its
core is projecting the future cash flows
of the business and discounting those
back at a relevant discount rate and so
that's exactly what we're trying to get
to here and so after the interviewer has
pushed you to come up with a few
different sources of revenue and costs
then they will show you this exhibit
which gives you information related to
the revenues which we can see comes from
ticket sales concessions merchandise
media rights and sponsorship slads and
also information related to the cost
which we can see is player salaries
front office costs sales and advertising
and Stadium SL facility costs okay so
I've written down a bunch of information
here related to two of the major revenue
streams and so we've been given a bunch
of information related to ticket sales
and concessions now it's important to
note here that there's also Revenue
which is coming from merchandise media
rights and ads sponsorships but we'll
get to those in a second and so your
interviewer will basically give you all
of this information and it'll be up to
you now to calculate the total revenue
per year generated by the baseball
stadium and so just to walk through the
math really quickly we have about 50,000
seats per Stadium of which 90% of those
are standard seats the standard seats
typically fill at a 56% fill rate and
they cost $25 per seat and the remaining
10% of seats in the stadium are actually
premium seats which fill at around 75%
per game and cost four times as much
$100 and another useful data point here
is that there are 80 home games per year
and so we're going to want to factor
that in when coming up with an annual
revenue figure for ticket sales and so
I'll do the math with you right here
just to walk you through so 90% of
50,000 means we're taking 10% off of
50,000 10% of 50,000 is 5,000 so this we
know is 45,000 standard seats in the
stadium now only about half of them
though 56% are going to be actually
filled and so what I'm actually going to
do is I'm going to round this down to
55% because that's a little bit easier
to to deal with and so we can take 50%
of 45k and we can take 5% of 45k and so
50% of 45k is roughly
22,000 and 5% of 45k is roughly 2 to
3,000 let's just say 3,000 so that means
25,000 and so if we add that together we
get roughly 25k seats going to put an
approximation here because that's a
round number and if we multiply 25,000
seats times the $25 per seat rate then
we get around
625k in total sales coming from standard
seats but we still have to calculate the
premium each share and so about 10% or
5,000 seats are premium seats in the
stadium 5,000 seats but only 75% of that
5,000 is actually going to be filled 75%
of 5,000 is roughly
3,750 and we multiply that by
$100 per ticket to get
375 K and ticket sales per game from
premium seats now I'm going to add the
375 plus the 625 which is a million so a
million in total revenue by the 80 home
games per year which means the total
revenue coming from ticket sales per
year is roughly 80
million okay so that's the major Revenue
stream from ticket sales now on the
concession side we have data that's
given to us related to the number of
fans buying concessions per game how
much they're spending on average and
again the number of Home gains which we
know is 80 and so this calculation here
is a little bit more simple because
we're just multiplying these together
and so 20,000 * 25 is roughly 500,000
and we multiply 500,000 * 80 to get us
to 40 million Okay so we've calculated
the total revenue coming from ticket
sales and concessions and as I mentioned
earlier there are actually three
additional revenue streams as well one
of those being merch another being media
rights and then the last one being
sponsorships slads and so in this
problem for Merch we're actually given
information that the team sells about 1
million pieces of merch per year at
around $50 per piece and they're going
to get a 20% Commission on that because
again often times merch is created by a
third party and it's just sold Through
The Branding that the team has so we
have 1 million pieces times $50 per
piece times 20% commission which gets us
to 20% of 50 million which is 10 million
so $10 million a year is coming from
merch now for the last two revenue
streams we're actually just given these
outright basically and so we know media
rights is actually going to be roughly
120 million per year and then
sponsorships and ads is about 50 million
per year and so if we total up all five
of these revenue streams what we'll
actually get is an aggregate Revenue per
year of around $300 million right down
there but we're not done here because
again we're trying to come up with the
valuation of the business and so we've
only finished coming up with the annual
revenue from the team and so we still
need to find out what the annual costs
from the business are and so you should
ask the interviewer if there's any
information related to costs as well and
he's actually going to give you in this
case interview scenario the main costs
associated with running this team and so
I've gone ahead and written the costs
down here but essentially player
salaries not surprisingly are the
biggest expense at 110 million front
office costs are 20 million sales and
advertising of around 50 million in
stadium facility costs just to keep the
lights on around 20 million and so your
total cost base is coming out to roughly
200 million per year and so now to
continue with the valuation we want to
find out what the annual cash flow or
the earnings before interest and taxes
for this company for this baseball team
is and so we start with our revenue and
then we take out our costs to get to our
pre-tax income otherwise known as ebit
earnings before interest in taxes and
then we want to take out our taxes to
get to the actual cash flow before
interest that we're going to use as part
of this valuation now there's one more
thing that we need which is the discount
rate because in order to calculate the
value of this baseball team we need to
have the annual cash flows but we also
need to Discount the future cash flows
back to the present and so you should go
ahead and ask your interviewer do we
have an appropriate discount rate to
Value this baseball team and they will
go ahead and tell you that 10% is the
discount rate okay so now we have enough
to start doing the math and so we have
our 300 million in annual revenue here L
our 200 100 million a year in costs
which means our annual ebit is going to
be just going to erase this 100 million
now the tax rate we should also clarify
you can usually ask your interviewer
something along the lines of should I
assume or can I assume a 20% tax rate in
this scenario actually they're going to
tell you to assume zero taxes for the
purpose of Simplicity this is not super
realistic but let's just go with it it
makes the math One Step easier and so
assuming that our annual cash flow is
around 100 million per year and we are
discounting this back as if it is a
perpetuity meaning that each year into
Infinity we assume that it's going to
continue to generate 100 million per
year that means all we need to do is we
need to divide 100 million by 10% which
is simply 1
billion okay so our valuation for this
baseball team right now is 1 billion now
the first thing you should do after you
do all of this math is you should
immediately step back and think to
yourself what does this number actually
mean in the context of this case
interview because a number by itself
means nothing unless it can be compared
to another relevant metric or another
data point right a discrete data point
means very little when it is looked at
in isolation and so if we compare the 1
billion valuation to this 1.1 billion
purchase price immediately what you
might notice is we're starting to wonder
does this make sense then because we're
going to be spending more money to buy
this team
than what it is currently worth and you
should try to have a discussion with
your interviewer at this point and let
him or her know what is going through
your head you should talk aloud and say
something along the lines of well okay
this is really interesting so it sounds
like we have a valuation number now of
about 1 billion but when I look at that
in relation to the purchase price that
was proposed earlier in this case of 1.1
billion looks like we're short of about
$100,000 now my initial gut instinct is
that this makes me question whether or
not this investment is even worth it but
at the same time there may be other
factors to consider that would still
make this a potentially good investment
for Alpha Capital including one of the
other buckets in my framework which was
synergies we haven't really talked about
the fact that even though the valuation
right now is 1 billion maybe there are a
number of levers and a number of things
that Alpha Capital can do to increase
the valuation of the business beyond
that 1.1 billion purchase price in year
zero and this valuation number was
calculated using historical numbers and
so again this is simply assuming that
Alpha Capital bought this company and
then did absolutely nothing to change
the revenue growth or the cost profile
of the baseball team which is highly
highly unlikely and so a good candidate
will notice this immediately and not
just take the analysis at face value
because oftentimes there's a second
order Insight underneath the initial
observation of hey it looks like the
valuation is actually less than the
purchase price and so after you bring
that up with the interviewer the
interviewer should actually show you a
number of additional exhibits related to
the potential synergies from this
transaction and so what we can see here
is actually there is a chart on the left
hand side showing the potential boost to
Total revenues based on four different
levers that the owner of the baseball
team has to drive Revenue up we have
Dynamic ticket pricing renegotiated
local media deals attract higher value
sponsors and revamped concessions
offerings and then on the right hand
side we have actually a team cost
comparison benchmarking our costs to The
League average now in a case interview
scenario again you want to walk the
interviewer through your thought process
and basically talk aloud like how I just
did to you and you want to first talk
about What observations you notice from
the charts and as you talk through it
this is going to help you start to think
about some initial insights that might
be interesting to dig into and so you
can say something again of along the
lines of hey so this is really fast
fascinating it looks like we have a lot
of different levers here to boost total
revenues it looks like Dynamic ticket
pricing is going to have the highest
impact right now by increasing revenues
by 4% um and on the right hand side I
can see that we have a team cost
comparison actually I can see that our
team's costs are higher on average than
the league Benchmark so it looks like
there's some room actually to bring down
some of these costs including our sales
and advertising costs and so if you've
been following along at this point you
probably know where we're headed next
which is to calculate an actual number
based on these new data points and so we
want to come up with the additional
revenue and the additional cost savings
associated with implementing all of
these potential Revenue levers and also
bringing down our costs to the league
Benchmark because in theory a private
Equity Firm with majority control over
this baseball team should be able to
make all of these changes within reason
really running out of whiteboard space
here but I'm going to put synergies
right here okay and so first let's
calculate the impact to revenue and then
we can calculate the impact to our costs
so it looks like based on the analysis
we have four levers here Dynamic ticket
pricing increases it by about 4%
renegotiated local media deals increases
Revenue by about 3% and attracting
higher value sponsors increases by 2%
and revamped concessions offerings is
going to increase by 1% and so if we
just add all of these up together that's
in theory a 10% increase to the Topline
and so if you remember Topline Revenue
was around 300 million as we calculated
earlier in this case and so an
additional an incremental 10% on top of
that would be an incremental $30 million
and so I'm just going to write here
increase plus 30 million and on the cost
savings side we can actually see that it
looks like the one cost bucket where
we're above the leak Benchmark is our
sales and advertising costs and it looks
like we can bring our sales and
advertising costs down from where it's
at right now which is about 50 million
if we remembered to 40 million which is
about a $10 million cost saving
opportunity and so I'm just going to
write down -10 million in costs right
down here in synergies and so in order
to calculate the impact on valuation
that these synergies are going to have
again we're going to take our
incremental revenue of 30 million less
our 10 million of cost savings which is
an incremental $20 million now how does
this $20 million from synergies Impact
our valuation well we need to Discount
this 20 million back by 10% again so 20
million divided by 10% which is going to
get us 200 million
dollar impact and so now if we add this
200 million to the 1 billion our new
valuation is actually I don't even know
if you can see this down here but our
new valuation is actually $1.2 billion
with the synergies factored in but now
this is really interesting because with
the synergies factored in we can see
that the valuation has finally exceeded
the $1.1 billion purchase price now
albeit not by a lot but it's still
significant because now this tells a
different story now at this stage in the
case the interviewer will probably ask
you what your thoughts are having done
all of this analysis on whether or not
Alpha Capital should make this
investment and this is where it's
important to go back to our framework
and to recall that the financial
considerations are very important but we
have yet to consider any of the
non-financial considerations and so it's
important to have a discussion with your
interviewer about look based on the
numbers it looks like the valuation is
now higher than the purchase price which
is great news but at the same time
there's still a lot of additional
diligence that we need to do to better
understand this baseball team and
specifically some of the non-financial
factors that I mentioned earlier on in
this case because at the end of the day
it doesn't matter that we have a $1.2
billion valuation if for example
implementing this new ownership and
putting all these changes into the
business is going to dramatically say
impact our fan base and a bunch of
people stop coming to our games or for
example if we can't even execute some of
the growth levers that would drive up
revenue or bring down our costs numbers
and big Financial models don't really
mean much if you cannot actually execute
on the plan and so the operational
component of this is actually really
really important to consider as well now
I could go on and on about the different
factors that we need to consider but in
a case interview scenario after a bit of
discussion about what other factors you
should consider the interviewer will ask
you to close the case with synthesis and
basically take everything that you've
learned today and bundle it up into a
recommendation for the CEO or in this
case your client which is a managing
director at Alpha capital and so a
typical way that this is asked is the
interviewer will say hey so in about 30
seconds the MD of alpha capital is going
to come through the door into the
conference room where we're working and
he's going to ask you for a
recommendation and an answer essentially
to the two questions that he posed at
the beginning of this project now what
would you tell him and that is your cue
to take 30 seconds just say awesome I'm
going to take about 30 seconds to put
together a recommendation and take 30
seconds and think through what you want
to recommend to the interviewer now it's
important to understand that in a case
interview scenario the actual
recommendation that you make is less
important than the way in which you
deliver the recommendation and whether
or not you back the recommendation up
with data points from your analysis but
just to help you out a common structure
that I like to follow with the synthesis
is recommendation risks and next steps
boom and so if you follow this structure
you'll start first with your
recommendation then you'll talk about
some potential risks and then you'll
talk about next steps and the point of
this is that bringing up risks
demonstrates that you're thoughtful
about what you're saying and you're not
just blindly assuming that whatever you
recommended is the best path and instead
that you're aware that yes things could
go wrong and the third piece of this is
where you can demonstrate thinking about
ways in which we can get more
comfortable with these risks or ways in
which we can learn a little bit more
about something to get more comfortable
and understand how risky something
actually is and so to give you an
example of how I might deliver this
recommendation I would say something
along the lines of awesome so thanks for
joining us today as you know we've been
doing a lot of work on understanding the
Phil Philadelphia philes and whether or
not this is a good investment and so
although our initial analysis yielded a
$1 billion valuation which was lower
than the $1.1 billion purchase price
after some further review on the
potential revenue and cost levers that
we have our expected valuation is
actually around $1.2 billion which
exceeds that purchase price now that
said there are a number of risks
associated with the success of this
investment namely around the execution
of actually implementing these revenue
and cost synergies and also with the fan
base and how they're going to react
to new ownership now what we would
recommend as next steps is to get more
comfortable with these unknowns is to do
some more market research on our
customer base and to understand their
General thoughts and perceptions on this
kind of a change as well as to look
further and potentially speak with
current management to better understand
the feasibility of implementing things
like Dynamic ticket pricing or lowering
our sales and advertising costs to the
leak Benchmark I hope that this was
helpful and if you have any questions
feel free to leave them in the comment
section below and I'll see you guys in
the next one peace